Imagine you are 15 years ago and you start the production on Halo 4.
You want to push the quality of the facial animations in your cutscenes, but you are
on an Xbox 360 with limited resources.
Hi, I'm Jerome and today I want not to talk about a specific paper per se, but I want
to talk about how Halo 4 managed to stream the facial animations inside of an Xbox 360
principal component analysis. So for those of you that might not remember what the cutscenes
were looking like, so this is Halo 4 on an Xbox 360 probably 11 years ago. And you can see that
the facial still holds up on these cutscenes, and it was all runtime cutscenes, so it was all
running on the consoles directly. But back then you couldn't execute a really expensive rig like
metahuman or having blend shapes and all of those kind of stuff. So you were limited on the kind
of rigs you could use. So the choice that Halo made was to use the same production pipeline
that they were using when they were doing, let's say, pre-rendered cutscenes. So doing mock apps,
doing facial mocap, doing all the stuff that we could do in pre-rendering, which was not the kind
of stuff that we could run at runtime back then because of the the the weights of all of those
rigs. And we could already record and we could already work with expensive rigs back then,
but it's really the runtime that wasn't the issues. So what Halo decided to do was to
to use the same pipeline as the pre-rendered one.
And then they would pre-render the facial animations
as vertex animation.
And that's the vertex animation
that they would try to stream on the console.
So you get rid of the entire rig.
You only have basically a big alumbic file
with all the vertices moving through times.
And that's what you try to stream on the console.
So I would do the same here.
What I would do first is that I would import
all the libraries I need and then I would create a material
because I will work with some things
outside of the usual framework.
Now, I've created official animations
using Omniverse Audio2Face.
So it's really a big alumbic file
with all my vertices moving.
And that's why it takes a bit of time to actually import
because it's quite massive.
And what I have is a head that is based on 123,000 triangles.
And that has a bit more than 60,000 vertices.
And it's only 220 frames of animations.
But really, because, as I said, we
moving every vertices through time basically means that if you have 200 frames of animations you have
200 different heads. So that's what I have in my frames here. It's 220 frames of 60,000 vertices
XYZ positions. So I get all my animations here and what I would do is that I would want to be able
to stream that to the graphic card. So I will create a vertex buffer for the vertices,
the positions, and I will make it as dynamic because I will update the values all the time
and I will do a second one with the normals. So I get both informations. I don't want to stream
normals. I would just keep them static. It's not perfect, but it makes it easier. And then I get
my vertex array, that's how we need to render everything. And then what I will do is that
I will create a shader because the framework is not expecting this kind of data. It's just
a simple shader. We just take the normal and the positions. I get the positions and I get the normal
and I multiply that by the view matrix and the position matrix. So it's correctly placed on screen
and then the fragment shader itself is the default one from the framework just to make sure
that I push everything I need inside of all my gbuffers and then I can create my program and I
can finally render that animation so what you could see is this character playing the animations
I've created, so as I said, 60,000 vertices, so there's no normal map, it's all inside
of the mesh directly, all the little bumps, it's fairly heavy mesh, and the way you render
this is really what I said, it's 220 different heads and I'm just uploading those heads on
the GPU every frame, so basically I take my buffer and I update what is inside of the
buffer with the correct frame at every frame. And it works, I mean I'm streaming the entire data.
Now you would have one big issue with this and the biggest issue is of course the size of what
you're trying to stream. In this case just with my 200 frames what I already have is 154 megabytes
of data, which is a lot. It's only one character, one head for 200 frames. It's not even an
entire cutscene. It's not multiple characters. So you don't have that kind of room on the disk.
So you will have to compress that data quite a lot. So basically, if you try to run it this way,
your CPU will be busy uncompressing the data,
your bus between the CPU and GPU
will be busy sending the data every time,
and your GPU will be just waiting
for the data to arrive most of the time.
So you will have to really focus
on how to be able to stream this kind of data.
And the solution that was used by Halo
was to go with the principal component analysis
to compress the data and send them with a lighter solution.
So that's what it will go through at this point.
So what is the principle component analysis?
Analysis is the fact that if you have a data
with a lot of dimensions,
you might want to reduce the number of dimensions.
So usually when you see the PCA explain what you will have
explain what you will have is, for instance, a bunch of 3D points scattered in a plot and you ask
the system, give me the line through all those points that represent the biggest variations.
So that's really what the principle component means is find the component that has the biggest
variations that represent the best the values. So you get one line through all your points.
And then you can ask for a second component that will be orthogonal to the first one and
that represent the second most important directions for all your data.
And you can remap your data inside of those two vectors inside of being in 3D.
So in statistics, for instance, you might have a population where you would ask for
the weights, the size, the age, the sleeping habits, what they eat, all that kind of stuff.
And you might do a PCA to reduce the number of features to a lower number so you could see if
there is a correlation between a bunch of values and if you start to get clusters of populations
in some places it will mean that a bunch of your values are actually related and that kind of stuff.
In our case we will actually do the same thing. What we have is 220 different heads
and so it will be considered as 220 features and what we want to say is that I want to reduce
those 220 frames to just, in my case, seven. So I will turn the 220 frames in seven different
components. In this case, it will be frames, but it's really seven different components.
And what the PC would allow us to do is to use those seven components
and reproject the data into the seven components and rebuild the animations. So really, what I'm
I'm using is the PCA implementation from scikit-learn.
So I will not rewrite PCA from scratch,
but I might do it in a different video
because there is paper talking about how to write
PCA for vertex animation.
So it might be interesting to see,
but at this point,
I just use the default scikit-learn implementations.
And it returns, you see, I'm fitting all my animations
And it returns me seven components,
and those seven components are basically seven heads.
So it is 184 floats,
so it's basically 60,000 vertices x, y, z, back to back.
And what I can do is that I can actually display
the different poses that he picked.
So that's one of the pose that he can use
to recompute my animations, that's a second one,
third, fourth, five, six, and seven.
So that's all the poses that he wants to use,
that he says that he can use to rebuild my animation.
And I can multiply those values so I can see
more or less what they will do.
All right, so you could see all the different poses.
What, oh, I'm doing this, I'm just picking the component,
I'm multiplying with a value because they will be really close.
And I'm adding the mean because a PCA works best
if you always remove the mean of all your values
before starting to compute the components.
So all the components are computed around zeros.
So you have to remember that you have a mean
that represents the average heads,
and then you get the components that represents
the offsets of that average head for all values.
That's what we have here.
And now that I have this, I can actually
say, well, you could transform my data into an animation that
would be basically is just an array now for the 220 frames
instead of having all the vertices that were used
is just the weights represent that you want to use to multiply each of the seven components you
have. So it's really a 220 frames, seven floats values. And I can render using that PCA. So what
I would do is again, I would use the scikit-learn inverse transform now. So I take the animations
I receive I do the reverse transform so it will give me back a head and I'm just moving it 30
centimeters on the side so I can render the ground truth so that's the first thing I'm
rendering here using the buffer I'm sending my true head and then I'm sending the one that has
been recomputed thanks to the PCA and what I have is the comparison between the two heads so
that the ground screws and that's the PCA animations. So remember this one is 220 different heads
and this one is just eight different heads so the mean plus seven components and seven floats for
every frame. So you're quite a lot smaller and you get the weights that are used for all the
different heads so for all the different components. So you see they study one times the
the first component plus minus five times
the second components and so on and so on.
And I give you that head.
So at this point, of course,
I have compressed the data quite a lot,
but I'm still decompressing the data on the CPU
and sending the full heads to the GPU.
So I haven't won anything.
So what you could do now is define a render
to try to make sure that we can render that
on the GPU directly.
And so the shader basically now just have,
instead of having one set of vertices,
it will have eight of them.
So it will get the mean, the first one is my mean,
and then all the different ones are the seven different
components.
And when you try to render this,
Basically, you have to send the seven floats you want to use
and how much you want to blend the difference head together.
And then you just accumulate the values.
It's just you take the mean, and then you
add the first component multiplied by the first values,
then the second component multiplied by the second values,
and so on, and so on.
And that's it.
And now you can build your buffers.
They don't need to be dynamic anymore,
because you will build them once,
and then you send them to the graphic card
and they will stay in VRAM.
You don't have to stream them anymore at every frames
and you build the programs, of course,
so you can render that.
And if I want to play my animations
and render this animation,
I better remove this.
What you have now is the only thing you have to send
at every frame is just a seven floats
and you could render your facial animations
just by sending seven floats,
because all the components now sits
in memory on your graphic card.
And that's how Halo 4 was able to achieve
this quality of facial animations in the cut scenes.
And interestingly, you could see
that one of the popular video you had back then
was done by Lord Z that actually make a mod and tweak the values of the animations.
And he said that he multiplied the facial animation by five and it got that with results that make a lot of people laugh.
And it's interesting to see that it really represents what was happening with the PCA
because it just multiplied all the values of animation by five and if I really do the same,
same, it would give me something quite similar. If I multiply it by 5, I get that same weight
result just basically because you are reconstructing your PCA with the wrong weights, you're pushing
them too far, all those weights, different weights basically. And I wanted to talk about
how Halo 4 did it because to my knowledge, it was one of the first time it was used.
I'm still not sure how Hélène Noir, if you remember that game, was doing the rendering.
But I was sure that Halo 4 was using PCA and I haven't seen any other game after using that
same technique and even Lord Z basically said that it only works on Halo 4 and it never
worked in any different LO. It was the only game as far as I know that ever used PCA to render
the facial animations instead of the cutscenes. And I find it interesting and I wanted to make
sure that it wasn't basically forgotten at some point. So I hope you liked it and see you next time.